How do you handle younger guys 18 to 30
with low T symptoms? Do you try to jump
start with HCG, etc. or straight to TRT?
What about when they're concerned about
future fertility?
>> Yeah, good question. Now, HCG is not not
a jump start because it shuts down their
natural production just like
testosterone. So, there's no point in
doing that. Um, I don't like the whole
put you on novidex or Clomid for a trial
period. I mean, if they've been on
anabolics, it might be reasonable if
they want to do that. They hadn't done a
PCT. I don't think PCTs are even
necessary, but it's a mental game with
people. So, some I have done that with a
couple guys in the past. I had like a
17-year-old come to see me when we were
a urologist. His testosterone was like
20, so you already know, you know, and
he'd been taking SARMMS. Um, and he
didn't want to start TRT. So I'm like,
"Okay, let's try two months of tmoxifen.
Try to just see if it ramps things up."
And then you got to come off of it to
see if it remains. And and it did. His
he rebound he may rebounded anyway
without that though. That's the thing.
But they were freaking out at the time.
So it's sort of a mental insurance thing
to do the the PCT. I like temoxifen over
Clom just because it's it's better
tolerated from a side effect standpoint.
But we just have a conversation. If it's
if it's an 18year-old, 20-year-old, it
depends on their maturity level, depends
on their lifestyle. A lot of these guys
are actually very mature for their age.
They've already been through the rabbit
trail of testing and then they end up
coming to me at the end. You know,
you're not going to find just for
somebody like me who's a cash pay
clinic. Most 18, 19 year olds aren't
going to want to come pay that anyway.
So, if they're coming to me, they're
probably have already been put through
the ringer with traditional doctors and
testing and been tried on things already
that didn't work. And I've had that from
a lot of guys who to maintain fertility
were put on freaking letol, crash their
estradile, they feel like crap, they
can't get an erection, and oh, their
testosterone is now 700. Who gives a
crap? They feel terrible. Um, so what we
do is we talk about testosterone. We
talk about the fertility potential risk.
It's not a given. Um, again, we're back
to expectation setting and informed
consent. And once we go through all
that, we just have a discussion about
what they want to do. And if they do
want to pursue TRT, I think a trial of
TRT is fine. I like cream better for
that purpose because it's in your system
quick, it's also out quick. So if they
end up not getting any benefit after two
or three months, it's out. They're
they're there not going to be any
long-term probably harm and probably not
from injections either for that matter.
But um we talk about fertility. For
those guys that are that young and they
don't have kids and they want to have
kids, we do an upfront semen analysis
because I want to know what their
starting baseline is. Um because what if
they're starting with a zero sperm
count? Well, if they don't know that and
then they get a test six months down the
road on TRT and then they they're zero,
what do they do? They blame the TRT when
it may not have been the T. Most a lot
of guys these days have very low sperm
counts just at baseline. Um, so I have
them check the semen analysis up front.
I tell them to freeze the sperm just as
an insurance policy unless they know for
a fact they would never do in vitro, but
most guys at 18 don't know that. Um, and
so I say freeze the sperm. That way
you've just got it on hand in case and
then we monitor down the road. And if
they want to go on hCG alongside the
TRT, we still space that out. I don't do
it up front because I don't want two
variables at once. I don't know that hCG
the whole time is necessary versus just
pulsing it in when needed with FSH if
their sperm counts go to zero. There's
no good way to know that. I know Dave
Lee's talked about that too. Again, I go
to the patient comfort level is what
matters for me. if they feel better
mentally going, "No, I just want to take
it every day or every whatever. I want
to take it alongside my TRT," that's
fine. We still got to monitor semen
analyses either way, you know. Um, and
if that starts tanking, then we talk
about adding in follical stimulating
hormone. Um, and for now, that's
available. There's a compounding
pharmacy making it that's affordable. If
that goes away, I don't know what we're
going to do. They'll I'll probably be ad
uh I'll probably be advising them to
seek out HMG from India to be honest
with you because that's still better
than coming off and getting on a
romantase inhibitor or Clomid or any of
that because you just feel like dog
crap.
>> Yeah.